This is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
SE radio is brought to you by the ITE
computer society and by it e software
magazine online at
computer.org/software.
Welcome listeners to software
engineering radio. I'm your host Aay
Ambad and today I'm joined by Sahaj
Kirk. Sahaj is the co-founder and CTO of
Whisper, a voicetoext AI that turns
speech into clear, polished writing in
every app. Prior to Whisper, he was an
AI engineer at Luminous Computing, where
he was the fifth employee and the AI
team lead designing the company's first
photonic system architecture to
accelerate large-scale AI workloads.
Sahaj is a graduate of Stanford
University and has published research
articles on topics in machine learning.
Sahajj, welcome to software engineering
radio.
>> Thanks for having me on the show.
>> Awesome. Well, is there anything else
about your background that you would
like to bring up before we dive into our
topic today?
>> No, I think that's great to get started.
I love technology. I love human behavior
and I love building things.
>> Brilliant. Brilliant. [clears throat]
So, today we will be talking about
ambiguity in human input. Before we get
into the specific details, let's go
ahead and introduce the problem of
ambiguity to our listeners. So when we
talk about ambiguity in human input,
what do you actually mean?
>> Yeah. In general, when I think of
ambiguity, I think of it as when
something could mean two or more
different things and it's genuinely not
possible to figure out what's the case.
And so this is the case, for example, if
I'm communicating with another person, I
might say something slightly cryptically
and the person listening might think
that I'm being ambiguous with respect to
what I've communicated. And it can also
be true for machine learning systems. If
you don't give them enough data or
enough context, it might be really hard
to figure out what's actually being
communicated or what's actually being
conveyed. And so there's some ambiguity
involved there.
>> Would you classify noise or error also
as ambiguity?
>> I think of ambiguity not as a function
of the output of the system. So errors
are a function of the output of the
system. Noise is a function of the input
of the system. Ambiguity is kind of
intrinsic as a property. Right? So if
you're communicating something and you
haven't given all the context or given
all of the information that's inherently
ambiguous and by adding more context,
adding more inputs, removing more noise,
I could get things to have less
ambiguity. And so when things are
ambiguous, what happens is it's easy to
have an error because it's possible to
interpret things one of two ways. So
it's highly related to noise, it's
highly related to errors, but I think of
it a little bit differently.
>> I see. As I seem to understand it,
ambiguity itself feels like an ambiguous
problem. Can you expand on that? How
does ambiguity even by definition feel
solvable?
>> Yeah. So things are ambiguous when it
comes to communication and when it comes
to real world interactions usually
because of a lack of context, right? So,
if I say that's great and I have a like
sight inflection that's paused at the
end of it versus that's great, that can
mean two very very different things. And
if I just saw the words that's great,
it's really hard to know which of those
it could be because it could in reality
be either of them. And so the kind of
only way to resolve ambiguity is with
more information, right? So if you just
had the words, you wouldn't be able to
tell what I meant. But if you have extra
context, for example, in that case, my
tone and my inflection, you might be
able to figure it out. You could also
figure it out lots of other ways. If you
know what I was saying just before it or
after it, so on and so forth.
>> So things like inflection points and
context, they seem to help humans quite
a lot in resolving ambiguity in
conversations. So context, structure,
things like that are very obvious to us.
>> Yeah. Why is it so intrinsically hard
for machine learning models?
>> It's hard for machine learning models
because they're only given a small set
of information at a point in time.
Right? So, we're having this
conversation. You've now already built
up the context of the last 3 or 4
minutes of what we've talked about to
make sense of every single statement I'm
making going forward. But most machine
learning models, they're just given a
little bit of information at a point in
time. They do a task and then they
forget about what's happened. Right?
Think about every interaction you have
with all these LLMs and AI systems and
how they learn a thing in one
conversation and then forget it the
moment after. And so that's where people
do a really good job at resolving
uncertainty and ambiguity. And these ML
systems have a much harder time doing
it.
>> We will get more into the details of
exactly how machine learning models do
that. But can we talk about the problem
you're solving at Whisper? What does a
voice first input system need to handle?
Yeah. So, our goal at Whisper is to
build the first voice interface that a
billion people can rely on as their
primary interaction with our computers.
And we're starting by solving for the
thing that people spend most of their
time doing, which is communicating. We
type a lot, hundreds of times a day. And
if you could speak to communicate to
your computer, it makes interacting way
more effortless. The challenge is that
when we speak, there's all sorts of
ambiguity. Sometimes you might be
mumbling into a microphone and there's a
fire truck going by in the background.
Sometimes you might correct yourself
midway through a sentence. Sometimes we
might not know whether you want
something to be more readable as a list
or be a semistructured thought dump
depending on who you're communicating
with. And so the ambiguity comes from
not fully being able to understand what
a person says, not fully being able to
understand how they might want it, etc.
And if you've ever used a voice system
like Siri or Alexa and it's ever
misunderstood you, sometimes those cases
are actually hard. Sometimes they're not
and sometimes it should have just gotten
it right. But sometimes they're actually
hard and those are the kinds of cases of
ambiguity that we're focused on solving
here at Whisper.
>> I feel like we all have experiences like
that with S. [laughter]
So let's move on to where the sort of
ambiguity shows up and talk about some
types of ambiguity when we speak
specifically about input. What are the
general categories of ambiguity that we
would encounter? For example, let's
think about something like sentence
structure as you mentioned within
context meanings of words. Can you talk
more about these different categories?
>> Yeah, absolutely. The ambiguity comes in
a couple of different ways. So the first
one is the style of how you want things
written. So for example, think about
somebody who's in Gen Z who's using this
to text a friend. Like the way that
people say things out loud and the way
they write their text to their friends
look very, very different. That same
person might also be using this to talk
to their boss at work. And the way that
they speak might still be the same
because we tend to speak the same way,
but the way that that has to be written
is going to look different. And so
ambiguity here or preferences come from
a variety of different ways. There's a
preference of how you want things
formatted and written. How you want it
to be cleaned up from the way we speak,
which is in lots and lots of run-on
sentences into a much more precise and
articulate version of what you're
saying. Or even really simple things
like people start words or sentences
with things like but or though or like.
And often the reason they do that is it
makes a message seem a lot more casual
and informal. And so in like Slack or
iMessage, I might want that to be
preserved. But if I'm writing a really
professional email to somebody, then I
actually want it to be cleaned up so
that I can go from the way that I sound
with my unstructured thoughts to a
really polished version of myself. So,
what I'm hearing is not only does the
context of what a user is saying
matters, but also what the user actually
wants, what their intent is.
>> That's right.
>> Where they're trying to convey.
>> That's right. And that's the kind of
context that most systems don't have.
The only way to figure it out is am I
messaging my wife, like my co-founder, a
person on my team, like my mom? I'm
going to do a different thing in each of
those cases. And there's no way to guess
that unless you have that kind of
information.
>> I would only imagine that this ambiguity
also shows up in thoughts beyond text.
So think of, for example, accents or
background noise, somebody talking very
far away from the mic. Would you
consider all of these as under the same
umbrella? And how would you solve that?
>> Absolutely. I just think of all of it as
intrinsic uncertainty. So what's the
uncertainty that you have? And the case
of accents, for example, with somebody
with a heavy accent saying two or three
words, if you don't know their accent up
front, it's actually very hard sometimes
to tell what language they're speaking.
And if you know their voice, if you know
the history of how they speak and what
their intonation sounds like, it's
actually much easier to figure out what
they're saying. And so in the case of
people who have different types of
accents, knowing their accent up front
itself helps. In the case of somebody
who's far away from a microphone and
might not be speaking too clearly, then
knowing the topic that you're speaking
about might help quite a bit. Or knowing
the person's voice and what it normally
sounds like so you can pick it out from
the background noise. That might also
help quite a bit. And so there's lots of
different sources that you could use to
understand this and it's how we
understand each other, right? Maybe my
favorite example of this is like
whenever I meet somebody with a new
accent, for the first couple minutes,
it's kind of hard for me to understand
what it is they're saying and after two
or three minutes of getting to know
them, it gets a lot easier very fast.
And that's the kind of way in which we
learn about how to understand different
people's accents in different
situations. And our goal when we're
building our technology is to do the
same thing for people. So as humans we
are able to associate different accents
and what words mean in that accent and
then take that into consideration when
we hear it again after a certain amount
of time is when you talk about machine
learning models are they also doing the
same thing how are they able to take in
context and keep that within context
while taking in more input as time goes
on.
>> Yeah. So, by default, these systems
aren't great at that, which is the
reason why they make lots of mistakes
that feel stupid and silly. They're
obvious to us, but they're not obvious
to these systems. And this is where LLMs
have been really powerful because LLM,
the whole discipline has been around
context engineering. How do you get the
context? How do you supply to the LLM?
How do you help it make sense of more
stuff and make better decisions? And one
of the core research problems we're
solving here at Whisper is how do you
give that kind of context to a speech
model or an audio model? Right now the
audio models that most people use don't
take this context into account. And so
if we can solve for that at a kind of
fundamental level then we can unlock
this capability in a way that works in
not just the text domain but also other
domains.
>> So you would want to as a first pass
want to solve this problem by tackling
the lowest common denominator and
building a generalized solution that
works for most cases. How would you go
about building one system for all users
in our for example conversation when
we're talking with different accents?
How are you able to build a single model
that takes into consideration all of
those things? Let me think of an example
here. Let's say I have a lot of people
with very interesting long names or who
use jargon a lot with acronyms. Systems
often get these wrong. What is the
impact here? How would you build a
singular system that tackles this
problem?
>> I would think of it the same way as how
people prompt LLMs. So if you're for
example coding and you say can you
update this function, then if the LLM
has access to your codebase, it knows
exactly what to do for you. And that's a
fully general system that works for each
person. And so the same thing, the same
idea could be applied to a speech model.
All of these systems are getting
unified. We're putting speech into LLM
backbones. And then if you can give it
all of this information as a prompt, as
information over time, suppose we know
the set of acronyms that you've used in
the past that you've fixed your output
to in the past, then we can use that
again going forward.
>> So is there a distinction between
inherent ambiguity where no right answer
really exists versus ambiguity that is
reducible where more context can help?
Can you talk a little more about that?
Yeah, maybe an example of that is the
question you just asked. So, whenever
there's ambiguity in what somebody's
saying, usually people ask clarifying or
follow-up questions. There was some
intrinsic uncertainty, some intrinsic
unknown in what they just said. And so,
people ask a follow-up question and they
might ask another follow-up question and
another follow-up question afterwards
because the topic's confusing. It
doesn't make sense, right? And so, a lot
of times there's inherent uncertainty.
The world is full of so much inherent
uncertainty like we can't predict the
future, right? And so we reveal it one
step at a time. We ask questions. We
clarify things that can help. And so at
the end of the day, even with what we're
building, one of the ways in which we
can continue to improve it is if we're
not sure what you said, what if we just
asked you, did you say this thing or did
you say this other thing? That's what we
do when we don't hear another person
when we're with them live.
>> Does that introduce friction in the user
experience? Certainly, which is why you
have to use it sparingly, right? If I
was talking to you and after every
single answer I gave you, you said,
"Could you say that again?" I would be
very annoyed if talking to you very
quickly. Like, I wouldn't want to be on
this call. But if you asked me that once
or twice, could you say that again? I
didn't quite get it. I'd be okay with
it, right? Because I know that that's
how I can feel confident that you've
understood me. And so, that's where it's
just important to navigate the
trade-offs really carefully here. What
about situations where, and I'm just
spitballing here, I say a sentence that
I want you to understand and you keep
asking me to repeat the same sentence
over and over again because you won't
get it. Do you find this a common
experience? And how would you deal with
it?
>> With us, it's pretty rare for what we're
building because usually if you speak a
little bit more clearly or maybe the
issue is that you have the wrong
microphone connected, like we can help
you figure out why it's not working.
When it's a person communicating with
another person, if you don't understand
it though and you keep just saying the
same question over and over again back
to a person saying, "Can you just state
it again?" You're probably never going
to make it anywhere, right? Instead, you
want to say, "Hey, I didn't understand
it that way that you said it. Like,
could you try explaining it to me a
different way?" Or, "Could you try
explaining it to me like I'm five or
something of that sort?" And so, the
idea here is to think about it as how
would you as a person actually try to
navigate this issue? How would you try
to clarify it? How would you try to make
sense of it? And to focus exactly on
that. I'm thinking of an example of
swiping on a keyboard to form a word and
when you swipe incorrectly or you swipe
and it is the same signature as another
word and you press the backspace button
you doing the same action again gives
you a new recommendation for a word that
is similar. Is it something like that
that we're thinking of here?
>> Exactly. That's right.
>> Awesome. This seems like a very
interesting problem. So I really want to
pivot now to talking about the training
of these models and what the
architectures look like for handling
ambiguity within context. So I'd imagine
you would want to build a generally
robust system at a model training level.
How would you provide the additional
context that is required to reduce
ambiguity? If you want to, for example,
take into consideration a person's tone
or their accent, how would you include
those kinds of metadata or additional
signals into the model training process?
>> Yeah, a good example of how we might do
that is the very last thing that you
said probably influences the next thing
that you're going to say. And so as part
of training these models, we can always
give it a prompt, which is the last
thing that you said, right? And use that
as information that helps you figure out
what the next thing is. And that prompt
might even include the audio clip of
your voice or some kind of
representation of your voice. And so by
training that into the model, then it
learns how to in the cases where things
are hard, make sense of that kind of
information and use it to resolve the
uncertainty. But how would you actually
go about constructing a data set that
captures all of this information?
>> So an example of this, if you look at a
lot of open source audio data sets, open
source audio data sets have many
different speakers in it, each of whom
say many different things. And so one
way of doing this, a simple way would
be, okay, great. you now have extra
information that you attach to every
example in the audio data set pertaining
to vocal characteristics of the speaker.
Now when you train the model, you could
train it with extra vocal information
and the audio and then you could add
lots of noise to the audio. Right? So
now you're basically forcing the model
to learn given this information about
the person's voice and given this really
bad audio clip, can you still make sense
of what they've said by using the extra
information that we've now given you?
And so that's a way you could even do
this taking some open source data off
the internet to make sense of it. And
that's like basically you can make the
data more ambiguous where you have to
rely more and more on this extra
information to figure out what's
actually true.
>> So you would require a lot of annotation
and labeling of this data set. Can you
talk more about the actual labeling
process?
>> Are you asking kind of generally from
the industry or for how we try to solve
it? I think let's talk about the
industry in general. How do you go about
labeling data sets? For our listeners,
>> yeah, there's basically two major ways
in the industry that people go about
labeling data. The first is by hiring
annotation firms, places like Meror,
Micro One and so on, where you can pay
people who are experts to take a look at
the data and annotate it. It's
expensive, it's timeconuming, it's
cumbersome, but it's one of the best
ways to get really gold standard data.
The second way is a little bit more of
like live interaction data. So this is
like what your thumbs up thumbs down UI
looks like in chat GPT where you can get
signal of whether a person liked a
response or not based on how they engage
with it and if they even give feedback
on it very directly. And so that's like
the two main methods, right? Figure out
what users are actually engaging with
and what they like and dislike and
figure out using external annotation
firms what to do. Do you capture for the
same input different kinds of valid
outputs that may be presented?
>> That's one of the ways of doing that.
Yeah. Whenever you've seen a chat GPT
UI, for example, where it says, do you
like option one or option two? That's
exactly what they're doing here. They're
trying to figure out what you prefer for
yourself and what you might prefer and
how that generalizes to other users as
well.
>> And that information is used for further
training.
>> That's typically how it's used. Yeah.
Can you talk more about instruction
tuning in the context of constraining
the generation space here? So how does
instruction tuning help a model when
something is in context what the output
should look?
>> Yeah. So instruction tuning is key for
getting these models to produce good
behaviors, right? So if you just ask
them to do things otherwise, if you give
them a prompt, they'll do whatever they
want to with it. Maybe they'll complete
the thought, they'll continue going on
with it, so on and so forth. The whole
point of instruction tuning is to get
the model to actually perform the kinds
of tasks that you want it to do. Whether
it's problem solving or in our case
speech decoding and speech understanding
or in chat GBT's case question answering
in a UI. And so instruction tuning is
all about constructing a data set that
helps you show the model what the
desired behavior is for it to produce at
test time and what kinds of instructions
should lead to that desired behavior.
And so it's a very key part of the
training recipe for most large scale
foundation models at this point. And
it's what people call post-training and
the training regime. So there's
pre-training of the whole model and
there's typically post-training which is
some type of instruction tuning or
fine-tuning to get the model to produce
the desired output.
>> Where are we currently in the technology
space with instruction tuning? Would you
say we are at a very good level of
understanding of how that works?
>> I would say the general frameworks
around instruction tuning are pretty
mature. There's different things that
you can do for post- training and the
hard parts are at the end of the day
clearly specifying what the model ought
to do. The techniques for how to get it
to do those things once you know what
you want it to do are reasonably well
understood as well as things in deep
learning get understood. Right? Things
in deep learning are still a blackbox in
a lot of ways, but the techniques are
pretty mature.
>> In an industry where demand for verified
skill has never been higher, prove you
have the foundation to deliver [music]
results with the ITE computer society's
new software professional certification
for emerging professionals.
Give your career the head start it
deserves. Visit
computer.org/certification
today.
So let's take a concrete example and can
you help me understand how you would for
example train a model to handle formal
versus casual tone based on the context
from a user.
>> So for example let's take this in the
context of chat GPT right where if
you've interacted with it you'll notice
that it has different personalities for
different people and so they found a way
to get it to generate outputs that way.
Typically what people will do is they'll
use a combination of like synthetic and
actual data generation to generate a
bunch of examples of different tones and
styles of the response. So maybe the
model originally will produce a variety
of types of responses and then you can
essentially grade those on the different
qualities that you want to produce.
Maybe formality versus casualness is one
of those axes. And then you could use
this to essentially train some kind of
reward where you assign some reward to
the model for doing a certain behavior
given a certain user's preference. And
you set up some kind of RL training
framework or supervised fine-tuning
framework for this to actually then give
the model a bunch of examples of if the
user said they want it formal, produce
some output that looks a little bit more
like this compared to this other thing.
And then that implicitly teaches these
models ah this is what a more formal
better aligned response would look like
for this user.
>> So we're talking about context like the
previous sentence or the tone or the
accent of a person or the kind of formal
or informal voice that you want to
provide. Right? and we're talking about
the data set and how we're able to label
this data set and build models based off
of that. For code generation models, we
have if there is a lot of context,
there's that challenge of code
compression, compressing the context so
that it can be fed back into the model.
Do you have similar issues when it comes
to representing context efficiently for
training voice-based models?
>> For sure. I think it's a little bit less
of an issue than with code models. The
reason why with coding this becomes such
an important thing is because the size
of a code base can be massive. And so
dealing with that is one of the
fundamental challenges of code and tool
calling. In our case, a lot of what
we're going to try and represent is like
the kinds of mistakes you fixed or the
kinds of mistakes that have happened in
the past or some sample of your voice so
we know what you're supposed to sound
like if you're speaking in a clear,
quiet environment. So there's a set of
things that we have to look at and
compression is a part of it I think more
than compression it's about selecting
the relevant information. So it's trying
to figure out okay like what's the topic
you're talking about like that's an
example of compression right compressing
down to the topic. If I know that
somebody is doing a radiology
annotation,
then knowing that that's the topic of
the conversation already helps me
understand the conversation way better
even if I was jumping in from scratch.
And so like different different kinds of
compression here include like how do you
represent a voice? How do you represent
a topic of a conversation? Especially if
we've had a long conversation like we've
already spoken for 30 minutes now for
example. How do we take all of the
information from this conversation to
help me understand the next sentence
that you're talking about? And there
it's about extracting, you know, the
relevant pieces of information, the
relevant maybe acronyms or things like
that, which are the kinds of terms that
are really important to get precise on.
>> Let's talk about scale for a second
here. When we think about architectural
patterns at inference time for these
machine learning models, how do you go
about actually working on inference time
to minimize the amount of latency you
have?
>> Inference time is really key, right? I
think one of the things that makes
models magical is when they're super
super fast and when they're slow, then
people get frustrated and impatient with
respect to what they can do. So a lot of
this has to do with how you architect
your services so that you might choose
the right model at the right time or you
might send the context ahead of time. So
for example with coding models like the
context often isn't fetched directly
when it's needed to be used. It's
fetched beforehand and represented and
compressed beforehand. And so there's a
lot of these different kinds of things
where you can like prefill for example
an LLM's cache or things like that so
that the moment you get a request you
can just handle that request very
directly.
>> Great. I want to talk more about
discussing the user behavior in
particular. Let's talk about revealed
preferences. What does it mean to learn
from user behavior rather than asking
them upfront what they mean?
>> Yeah. So, one example of this is if you
asked me to describe my writing style,
I'd have a pretty hard time like
actually describing in words all the
details of my writing style. And if you
asked me how I write differently in my
email versus in Slack versus on
iMessage, I'd have a really really hard
time precisely articulating even though
I know they're different. And so this is
where in general it becomes really
important to understand what somebody
might want even if they don't know how
to put words to it. Right? So that's
what I call revealed preferences.
Revealed preferences are when an action
that somebody takes tells you something
about what they like or dislike. And so
in our case, for example, the principle
that we hold is if you speak into your
computer and you fix a mistake twice,
ideally you shouldn't have to fix it
again, right? we should be able to learn
that from you and personalize it to your
desired output. And there's a lot of
things that go into that where it's
basically, hey, when you're fixing
something, you know, what preference
does that reveal for you about what
you'd rather, whether it's something
about your accent or something about the
style in which you write or so on and so
forth, and then how do we fold that back
in so you don't have to tell us the next
time.
>> So, let's expand on this example that
you just talked about. When a user types
something or inputs something and they
have to correct themselves multiple
times, they press the backspace key, for
example, that in itself is a signal that
indicates the user's preference that is
done without explicit feedback.
>> That's right.
>> Are there similar signals that indicate
to you what the user's preferences are
other than correcting themselves? I
think that's the biggest one because
correcting yourself is ultimately the
worst possible thing that can happen
when it comes to using voice, right?
It's like you didn't trust the output.
You weren't able to use it immediately.
And so that's what's really important to
us. I think a lot of other companies do
different things. So for example, places
like Tik Tok or reals, they learn like
you don't tell them upfront. I like
videos about like AI generated teddy
bears that move around and like dance
their arms. Although I've seen that
content like this is fairly popular on
reals and Tik Tok and what they do is
they look at your engagement statistics,
right? So how long did you continue
watching on Tik Tok after seeing that
piece of content and that tells you
something about the user's preference.
We don't use information like that, but
that's uh certainly something that a lot
of companies do.
>> Personalization might also come into
picture alongside of context and intent.
>> Yeah. For example, I'm thinking if a
person who is early Gen Z prefers no
capitalization but capitalizes names in
particular, you could infer that
information from their age when they try
to initially set up. Is that something
that you work on?
>> It is. It is. And I think what we've
learned is like demographic
characteristics will teach you a little
bit, but the particularities and nuances
of these preferences are pretty hard to
get from demographics. And so instead of
trying to do it like based on kind of
broad buckets like that, we're trying to
do it in a more general way where we
see, oh, based on certain things that
you do, what is it that you might like
and how do we get it so that you don't
have to think about that as a user? How
do you balance personalization with
consistency? What if as a user I'm
incredibly inconsistent and stocastic?
How do you decide what to learn from a
user like that?
>> It's a great example of the inherent
ambiguity question that you asked. Like
sometimes we're going to do one thing,
sometimes we'll do another thing, and
there's like no real rhyme or reason to
why. And I mean, in those cases, if we
learn inconsistent things from people,
we'll probably produce slightly
inconsistent outputs. Sometimes we'll do
one thing, sometimes we'll do the other
thing. And the unfortunate reality is
like we might not perfectly know in that
moment, in that mood that you were in,
what was the exact thing that you
wanted. But so long as it feels like
you, feels like it gets you and feels
like it gets the spectrum of things that
you do, typically people feel pretty
comfortable with using these kinds of
systems. And so I would say yes. Yes.
And it's probably okay from from what we
build. I'm imagining a user whose
behavior is inconsistent cannot complain
about getting inconsistent outputs.
>> People can complain about anything they
want to complain about. At the end of
the day, the user is right in what they
want. And they might just not be able to
get what they want because of that, but
you know, pe people will complain. It's
a moving target. And the important thing
for us is to give people what they'd
like, right? At the end of the day,
that's what we can control.
>> Especially in a fastmoving field like
ours.
>> Absolutely.
>> So, let's talk about AI writing. Writing
using AI is now very very common and we
know that it generally regresses toward
the mean becoming the default, right?
Why does this happen and how do we fight
this? Do you think this is a training
problem or an inference problem or a mix
of both?
I think it's a problem of people
relegating their thinking to the AIS.
Like the thing that's special about us
is our beliefs and what we care about
and what makes us human. And the moment
we start relegating most of that kind of
stuff to tools, then we lose that about
ourselves, right? Like what's special
about voice is it's uniquely us, right?
It's uniquely something that we can do.
And I think the antidotes to this tend
to be really focusing on what's
important to us as people. So, one of
the things that I've started to like
when I use AI tools for writing is that
I focus entirely on, hey, here's the
audience of this message. Here's what I
want them to take away. Here's a brain
dump of all the content that I want them
to understand. can you help me make it
as understandable for that person as
possible, knowing that I like to
communicate things this set of ways? And
I found that with the latest set of
models, they can actually do that pretty
reliably in a way that feels
representative to me, my ideas, what I
want the person to understand, so on and
so forth. And so I think there's this
aspect of like if you ask an AI to
generate a blog post from like a bunch
of generic content, it will come up with
something that sounds so plausibly good
and yet says nothing interesting. But if
you steer it and you say like, "Hey,
here's like what I want a person to take
away. Here's the main interesting
things. Here's how the points tie
together. Here's like the narrative arc
that I'd like to tell. Like can you help
me tell it that way?" Then all of a
sudden you've kind of thought about what
do you want the person to understand and
you can tell a really interesting story
and so that's like the that's the
antidote that I see in my mind.
>> So the user introducing more granularity
into the kind of
>> Exactly. Exactly. It's like the only way
is for me to convey what I want. Right.
And if I do that then it will do what I
want and it will sound more and more
like me. And I think the the aspects of
tone and style, those will probably be a
little bit more easily solvable, right?
Because you can analyze a lot of a
person's writing and their email and
their Slack and so on. You can construct
information about their style and tone.
But what is harder is even then the
content of what you communicate, like if
the content of what you communicate
could entirely have been automated, like
it wasn't really a very interesting
piece of communication anyways, right?
and you were just talking to a chatbot
and that's fine and plenty of
interactions are going to be talking to
a chatbot instead of talking to a
person. But for anything where I do want
to talk to a person, I want to know what
they have to say, right? And like
perfectly formulating the words for a
written document, like that's fine. That
that won't be a thing that people do
nearly as much as they used to. But the
ideas that they want to convey, like
that's got to come from somebody. That's
the biggest challenge with AI is it is
able to understand a lot of the intent
and the ideas but not express it as well
as a human would. But I want to pivot to
a different topic. Maybe a little
personal question. I'm a person who
speaks a lot of languages and anybody
who speaks a lot of languages usually
when they talk to other people they
switch between them, right? I speak
Spanish and English for example. I work
with people who speak both languages. So
sometimes it's natural to you switch
contexts or sometimes switch
mid-sentence. If I am doing that, how or
would a ambiguity based solution be able
to handle that kind of mixed language
input? Can you talk more about that?
>> The way I think about it is if you mix
two languages, it's almost like you're
speaking a third language that contains
a little bit of both. And [snorts] so
that's a language of its own and it has
lots of characteristics that are shared
with other languages. And ultimately it
comes down to a data problem, right?
Very little data on the internet from
audio data has a mix of languages. And
that's the reason why most voice systems
are pretty bad at that kind of stuff.
But if you understand both languages, if
you understand the the third intermixed
language, it should be like learning a
new language. That's really it.
Effectively models are able to portray
in a embedding space words that we talk
about. So when we talk in two languages
from in one sentence that is still being
embedded into the same space as one
language. So you're right in saying
that's a third new language in itself.
So we spoke about personalization and
learning from user behavior. Let's talk
about the user experience a little more.
How do we communicate uncertainty with
users without degrading their experience
using these models?
I think that's generally a pretty hard
question cuz people don't really like
being told that they're not sure about
something like that's um it's not what
people want. I think generally the way I
think about it is like think about when
you're typing on a keyboard you see
three autocorrect suggestions. That kind
of user experience is not bad because
it's like, oh, maybe it's one of these
three things. They can click a button
and fix it when there's uncertainty, but
it presents certainty in the text box,
right? Like you got the full full thing
that you typed out and you just got a
couple buttons you can tap to fix it if
you need to. That's how I tend to think
about that.
>> Giving users too many choices leads to
more confusion.
>> Exactly. If they can go fix it
afterwards, they can go fix it
afterwards. It's frustrating. It's a
little paper cut that you're getting as
a user, but it's solvable.
>> So, if I am saying a sentence that
includes uncommon names or acronyms,
>> would you rather have the system
interpret it incorrectly and have the
user correct it?
>> I think that's probably the first thing
that happens, right? Where once they do
that once, then I don't want to make
that mistake again from our end, right?
That's how we work on that. And I think
the other part of it is sometimes people
will just say like oh
spelled a m e y for example and framing
things that way just however people will
naturally try to communicate that when
there's a little bit of uncertainty in
the spelling we just have to handle that
for you. So that seems like a graceful
fall back in design to be able to tell
the user, hey, if you think that a name
that you're going to say is going to be
hard for me to decipher, spell it out
for me.
>> It's the same way that we do if we're
talking on the phone with somebody and
we want to make sure they get it right.
>> Exactly. It's helpful to learn the
natural alphabet then. [laughter]
So recommendation systems often show
multiple options because they don't know
any user preference initially. Should
text and voice systems be doing the same
thing generally speaking?
>> No. I I tend to think of all of this as
mirroring human interactions. Like if
you
said the same thing four different ways
before I had a chance to try to
understand what you were saying, like
that would be a kind of painful
interaction between the two of us,
right? or like whenever I get the chatbt
UI with two different things like I kind
of shudder a little bit inside cuz I'm
like now I have to read both of these
things and or I don't have to right I I
usually just read one of them and then
I'm just kind of confused and
overwhelmed honestly speaking which is
where it's like that's not where it's
useful on on the recommendation side
it's as a user I'm trying to explore
what I want and so I'm happy to see
multiple things because my goal was to
see multiple things if I search for
something my goal was to see multiple
things and so it's all about fulfilling
ing the user promise, right? If I asked
you to find restaurants for us to go to
dinner to tonight, you might suggest two
or three options. That way, like I have
some choice as well, right? And so
that's how I think about it's all in
parallel to how people interact with
people. We want to make that the same
way that you interact with devices.
>> Let's switch gears and talk about
resolution and evaluation of these
models. How would you evaluate whether a
system that you build is handling
ambiguity well enough?
>> There's two parts of it. One part is
consistency, right? So when things are
ambiguous, ideally you want a system to
make a consistent decision. And then the
second part is knowing whether more of
it could be resolved. Like more context
could help make sense of more of these
things. And like one of the ways you
could do this is we we just talked about
recommener systems, right? where it can
output five guesses of what you might
want. We could have our systems do the
same and we could see, hey, how much
inconsistency is there between the top
five guesses of what we think is the
right answer? And are we consistently
ranking them in some kind of systematic
way? So there's a predictable behavior
and there's some level of inconsistency
or uncertainty in thinking, oh, maybe
it's this or that or that or that. Is
there some kind of output set that you
would be measuring results in contrast
with to be able to get specific metrics
out for systems like this?
>> I think basically the way that we do it
is we take the examples where we know
the answer and maybe it's just really
hard to predict the answer given the
input, right? But we know what the
answer is. And so the level of ambiguity
left in the system is how much you still
get things wrong given that. And the
measure of how much we're able to reduce
that ambiguity is by seeing how much we
can get things right by giving more and
more context or more intelligence to
these models. Right? Either one of those
things can help it.
Looking for a way to stand out in a
competitive job market. Whether you're
trying to land your first contributor
role or prove you can deliver, take the
next step in your career with the new
software professional certification from
the ITE computer society.
Sign up today at
computer.org/certification.
So let's think about online evaluation.
What kind of signals from production
usage by users tell you whether you're
getting things right or not? Initially
we discussed examples where users change
the output that you produced for them.
That is obviously one case. Are there
other metrics that you can talk about
that you you might use?
>> I think it's things like that and things
like engagement, right? Like if you use
it once and then you never try it again.
We probably did a pretty bad job with
that first thing. And if you use it once
and then you come back a hundred more
times, you probably did okay, right? At
least okay, maybe great. And so this is
like the set of I'd say two major things
right how did the person interact with
the output itself and how long do they
spend with it you know you have to be
careful here right like in chat GPT if
you keep saying no that's not what I
meant please try again like 20 times
that's also an example of you not doing
something right even though the person's
engaging multiple times but chances are
if they come back day after day right
that's that's one of the best predictors
of doing a better job than before. So
it's all about users engaging over and
over and us collecting information based
on their usage to set up feedback loops.
Right. Exactly. Those feedback loops do
they help improve the model over time?
>> Yeah. For it improves the model over
time and also more than more importantly
than that it tailors the model to you as
a user. Right. So, as we talked about
like as you fix more mistakes, we know
more and more about how to not make
those mistakes for that user. That might
not transfer to another person. The
topics you speak about, the acronyms,
the conversational styles, so on and so
forth are going to be different for each
person, but we can make that pretty
consistent.
>> So, it seems like there are lessons in
our discussion that we're having here
that generalize beyond just voice
processing.
>> Yeah. Yeah, talking about different
types of models. You work on voice at
whisper, but these problems seem to
appear everywhere. Think of chats like
chat GPT to co-pilots, recommendation
engines. What type of lessons about
ambiguity would you say would transfer
across the industry?
>> I think most of them I think like almost
all of these things that I'm talking
about are exercises in how deep learning
works today and how people reason about
things. Like even if you were to think
about ML for biology, I'm sure a lot of
these same things apply where if you
give these models for biology or for
medical reasoning more and more context,
their ability to make good decisions
will be better. And so like maybe the
simple one sentence version of this is
ambiguity gets resolved with more
context. The more context you can give a
system, the better it does. And if you
find that it's not doing nearly as well
as you want it to, see if you can give
it that context, right? And that's true
for everything we've seen in this era of
deep learning, right? Where the products
that do this well become really
delightful to use and the products that
don't are pretty frustrating.
>> So we want to build models that model
behaviors that humans usually have.
>> Yep.
>> As well as they can. There are listeners
of ours who would be building chat
interfaces or LLM powered applications
that might also run into ambiguity
related issues. What are some things
that they should start thinking about
when it comes to resolving that type of
ambiguity?
>> I think it all comes back to
understanding what is it that your users
want and how do you get it for them?
Like when it comes to building new
products like that, it always starts
with what's the problem you're solving?
Why is it important to them? Then how do
we make sure we get that thing to them?
And that itself is an exercise in
understanding what people really want
like that's the most important problem
when building new products. Once you
know that then you can go and solve the
technical and product and go to market
challenges related to it and keep
building from there. So let's say I am a
user who is building something on GitHub
right now for code generation and I am
struggling with users who are providing
me with underspecified prompts.
>> So a lot of ambiguity in the input
itself. When should I decide that my
tool should ask for clarification versus
infer it from code context?
>> I mean the way claude code has done this
is absolutely brilliant, right? Because
it asks just just the right number of
questions. I think there's parts of it
where it's a trade-off where one you
first figure out can I guess it
automatically based on the things that I
have access to and then if if the
model's unconfident in that is when it's
time to ask questions and then it's
about rank ordering and prioritizing
what questions to ask like you only get
so much patience from a user in coding
settings maybe you get two or three
questions that you can ask somebody and
so then it's about ranking
>> ranking the most important ones, the
ones that are going to affect the
outcome the most and asking just those
things.
>> There are more workflows like GSD and
Ralph that go into details on how to
resolve this sort of ambiguity, but this
has been very helpful. I thank you so
much for your time today. Before we wrap
up, would you like to direct our
listeners to where they can find out
more about you and your company?
>> Yeah, you can check out the company and
the product at www.wisporflow.ai.
AI and you can see our careers page to
learn more about joining.
>> Awesome. Well, Sah, thank you so much
for speaking with software engineering
radio. Thank you for listening. I'm your
host, Ame. See you next time.
>> Thanks for having me on the show. A
[music]
>> thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by E
Software Magazine. For more about the
podcast, including other episodes, visit
our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, [music]
or through our Slack channel at
seradio.slack.com.
[music] You can also email us at
teamseradio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under creative common
license 2.5. Thanks for listening.